Hi, welcome back to Nagarjuna
and the emptiness of the Medicine Buddha.
And we've reached the next
chapter which is Chapter 12.
Don't forget our goal
is to finish 27 chapters
in five years.
And this is the third year and
we're making good progress.
We're already to the twelfth chapter.
And again this is a parīkṣā
(pariksha) which means what?
An investigation.
And this time we're going to
investigate duḥkha (duhkha).
- [Woman] Suffering.
- Suffering, yay!
So I don't know about you,
but you feel like, oh finally
he got to this subject.
I would like to investigate
all the messing in my life,
all the messes in my life.
I would like to investigate and
find out why they're happening.
So like why did this COVID come
and why is my partner grumpy sometimes?
Why does my dog pee in the house?
And big things like that, you know.
So this is called
BDAG GIS BYAS PA DANG
GZHAN GYIS BYAS PA BRTAG PA
which means an examination
of investigation
of is the pain, the trouble in my life,
is it coming from me?
Or is it coming from something else?
And the "me" here is BDAG.
So that can also mean,
does the trouble in my life
come from the trouble in my life,
or does it come from something else?
Does the trouble in my life come
from itself or from something else?
I'll say it again.
Do the problems in my life come
from the problems in my life,
or do they come from something else?
Then, actually, Nagarjuna
splits it into two.
Do the problems in my life
come from the problems in my life,
or do they come from something else?
And who gives me the problems in my life?
Is it me or is it somebody else?
Who gives me trouble?
Is it always me giving myself trouble?
So we're discussing self and other
in two different contexts.
Does the pain cause itself,
or does something else cause the pain?
Do I cause myself pain?
Do I pain myself,
or does someone else pain me?
So those are the questions
that we're going to explore in chapter 12.
Let's go to the first verse.
,KHA CIG SDUG BSNGAL BDAG GIS BYAS,
,GZHAN GYIS BYAS DANG GNYI GAS BYAS,
,RGYU MED PA LAS 'BYUNG BAR 'DOD,
,DE NI BYA BAR MI RUNG NGO,
Then Nagarjuna gives you four options
about: does pain cause itself?
Forget me or you.
That's not what we're talking
about in the first part.
We're talking about,
does the trouble in my life
cause the trouble in my life,
or does something else than the trouble
in my life cause the trouble in my life?
And Nagarjuna starts out
and he says, you know,
this question is discussed
by four different groups of people.
There's four philosophical schools
in ancient India, 2,000 years ago,
who have an opinion on this question.
KHA CIG means different
people say different things.
What?
First choice. Some of them say
SDUG BSNGAL BDAG GIS BYAS
The trouble in my life comes
from the trouble in my life.
That's the first opinion.
All right? From itself.
Now, second opinion.
GZHAN GYIS BYAS
What's that?
Yeah, because somebody else...
Something other than
the trouble in my life
causes the trouble in my life.
That's the second opinion.
Third opinion.
GNYI GAS BYAS
It's both of you guys.
The suffering, the trouble in your life
causes the trouble in your life,
and there's things that aren't
the trouble in your life
that also bring trouble in your life.
Exactly the same thing.
Third choice.
Oh! RGYU MED
Yeah, neither one.
Nothing causes the trouble in
your life. It just happens.
LAS 'BYUNG BAR 'DOD
DE NI BYA BAR MI RUNG NGO
Hey, you're all wrong.
Wait a minute. One of
them has to be right.
There's only four possibilities.
He says no.
And I think this is a good
place to learn some Sanskrit.
So in different parts of these classes
we've been learning
different kinds of Sanskrit.
And there's some Sanskrit right here
which I thought it would be useful
to throw it in right away.
And that is: by itself; by something else;
by both; by neither.
Let's learn the Sanskrit for
those four possibilities.
Then let's learn the Sanskrit
for trouble in your life
because that's how we spend our life.
So here's the Sanskrit.
The first one, svayaṃ kṛta (svayam kirta),
svayam kirta.
Svayam means came from itself.
Kirta means made.
The trouble in your life svayam
kirta, "comes from itself."
The trouble in your
life comes from itself.
In Tibetan, BDAG GIS BYAS
-- it comes from itself.
This "svaya" in Sanskrit has
pieces like "su" and "aya".
And su means yourself.
And aya makes it a noun, selfness.
And we see this su in English
when we say "suicide".
"Cide" means to kill.
And "sui" means yourself.
Self comes from sui, su,
and solitary comes from su.
So all of those words
come from this svaya.
Also the Indo-European is s(w)e.
And that came into "self" and "secret".
So all of these words meaning self.
Kirta.
[coughing]
Kirta comes from a verb √kṛ
(kir) which means "to do".
That's the root of the word karma.
And kir just in general
means "to do" something.
English cognates are
cereal, create, and karma.
Cereal. There's a time in history
when C changed to S sound.
And originally it was ka, so
"create" and then "cereal".
All right, so these all mean "to make".
Now, the second option is that things are
parakṛta (parakirta).
The trouble in my life
comes from something
other than the trouble in my life,
or the trouble in my life is caused
by someone else other than me.
Second choice.
"Para" just means
somebody else, other guys.
All right, third choice.
Dvābhyāṃ kṛta (dvabhyan kirta),
dvabhyan kirta.
The trouble in my life comes from both,
me and other people or by itself
and from other things, both.
Dva means two.
That's why the number two has a W in it.
It's also, the W is the B
in "bicycle", for example.
And the word "divide".
Or this fourth choice
is "ahetuka", ahetuka.
Hetu means?
- [Woman] Cause.
- Cause. A?
- [Woman] Not.
- Not, okay.
"Ka" means made by.
Yeah, not made by causes, ahetuka.
So the last possibility is that
the trouble in your life
just comes to you at random.
It's not brought about by
you or by other people.
It doesn't come from itself.
It doesn't come from something else.
I like this word, duḥkham (duhkham).
I mean, I don't like
duhkham, but I like the word.
Duhkha.
Duh stands for D-U-S.
The S changes to H in this context.
And so "dus" means bad.
I don't know, did you call people
[expletive] in your high school?
[chuckling]
I'm sorry. Forget that.
Dus means bad.
It came into English as D-Y-S.
I think through the Greek,
"dysfunctional" or "disease".
And then the "kha" means
the open hub of a wheel.
Traditionally duhkha is explained
as meaning "a squeaky wheel".
You know, they say what?
The squeaky wheel makes the most noise.
- [Woman] The squeaky
wheel gets the grease.
- Oh yeah.
Anyway, troublesome people
make the most noise,
something like that.
So duhkha is traditionally explained
as being a bad connection
on your wheel on your cart.
And then it goes...
[mimicking squeaking]
Kha is also found in
Indo-European as √ghāi, ghai.
That means...
[mimicking yawning]
Ghai.
It means to yawn or to
gape with your mouth.
So duhkha basically is just a big mouth.
A big, bad mouth.
And it means trouble.
Where does the duhkha,
where does the trouble might've come from?
Is it svayan kirta?
Svayan kirta, does it
come from me somehow?
Parakirta, does it come
from somebody else somehow?
Dvabhyan kirta, is it coming
from me and other people?
Or is it ahetuka?
Or does it just happen?
Things happen.
All right that's the chapter
that we're going to be looking at.
Let's go to the next verse.
,GAL TE BDAG GIS BYAS GYUR NA,
,DE PHYIR BRTEN NAS 'BYUNG MI 'GYUR,
,GANG PHYIR PHUNG PO 'DI DAG LA,
,BRTEN NAS PHUNG PO DE DAG 'BYUNG,
When we're discussing the possibility
that pain has come from pain itself,
Nagarjuna says, what I mean is,
did the mortal falling
apart body that you have
and mind that you have now,
did that come from a
mortal falling apart body
and mind in the past life?
That's what it means when he says
that suffering causes suffering itself.
Is it the nature of your
body and mind to suffer?
And let's look at the possibility
that your body and mind
which are falling apart,
and you can't stop it normally.
And it's funny the things that
people do to try to stop it.
I think half the things we try to do
to stop the suffering, the falling
apart of our body and mind,
they just accelerate the falling
apart of our body and mind.
Anyway.
GAL TE, he says here,
So Nagarjuna says, "When I talk
about pain coming from pain
"what I'm really talking about
"is what caused your
body and mind right now
"that's falling apart."
And let's look at the first possibility
that it's coming from the
same thing in the past.
You had a body and mind
that was falling apart.
And then it created a body
and mind that's falling apart.
So here we go.
GAL TE BDAG GIS BYAS GYUR NA
If the problems you have in your life
are coming from the problems in your life,
DE PHYIR BRTEN NAS 'BYUNG MI 'GYUR
then we can say that it did not come about
by depending on something else.
If the trouble in your
life has been caused
by the trouble in your life,
then we can say there's
no dependence there.
It's not like the trouble in your life
has to depend on trouble in your life
because it's already trouble in your life.
GANG PHYIR PHUNG PO 'DI DAG LA
BRTEN NAS PHUNG PO DE DAG 'BYUNG
Actually, I should say that
even when you say suffering...
Now, Nagarjuna is correcting the guy.
I would say though that if you have
a body and mind that's falling apart,
it's a sign that you had a body and mind
that was falling apart before.
So maybe last life you had
a body and mind that was falling apart.
You did things.
You did not so nice things
because your body and
mind was falling apart.
And then now in this life your body
and mind is falling apart.
So falling apart causes falling apart.
That's okay.
And then by the way, he says,
"In that case, if pain causes pain,
then could you have come from your death?"
And he says no.
It's not correct to say
that the falling apart
body and mind of your last life
caused the falling apart
body and mind of this life
because the body and mind falling
apart in this life started,
and that one was ending.
So if they're the same thing,
they wouldn't have a cause and effect.
It could not have come from my death.
I cannot come from my death.
Picture.
GANG GI PHYIR NA 'CHI DUS
KYI SDUG BSNGAL GYI PHUNG PO
'DI DAG LA BRTEN NAS SKYE
BA'I CHAR GTOGS KYI PHUNG PO
DE DAG 'BYUNG BA'I PHYIR,
SDUG BSNGAL DE CHOS CAN
SDUG BSNGAL RANG YOD NA RANG
GIS BSKYED MI DGOS SHING
MED NA RANG GIS BSKYED MI NUS PA'I PHYIR,
If your suffering body
and mind came from your
past suffering body
and mind, then since
your past body and mind
where already suffering, they didn't have
to create more suffering because
they were already suffering.
Nobody made them suffering.
The cause was suffering.
So the result was suffering.
So no new suffering was made.
No new suffering was made.
SDUG BSNGAL RANG YOD NA
RANG GIS BSKYED MI DGOS
If your nature is to suffer,
then no one has to make you suffer.
SHING MED NA RANG GIS BSKYED MI NUS
If your nature is to suffer,
then you don't have to do anything.
You're going to suffer anyway.
If your nature is not to suffer,
and you try to make yourself suffer,
you couldn't do it anyway.
If your nature is not to suffer,
then nothing could make you suffer.
If your nature is to suffer,
then nobody would have to make you suffer
because you're already suffering.
Next verse.
,GAL TE 'DI LAS DE GZHAN ZHING,
,GAL TE DE LAS 'DI GZHAN NA,
,SDUG BSNGAL GZHAN GYIS BYAS 'GYUR ZHING,
,GZHAN DE DAG GIS DE BYAS 'GYUR,
This is how Choney Lama reads this one.
GAL TE 'DI LAS DE GZHAN ZHING
If the body and mind falling apart
that you took in this life was coming from
body and mind at your last death,
which is GZHAN.
GZHAN means is the falling
apart body and mind of this life
is it your body and mind
falling apart in your last life?
Yes or no?
Is your body and mind
falling apart in this life
your body and mind falling
apart in your last life?
- Are they the same thing?
- No, they are the same experience,
but one happens first and
then the other one happens.
So can we say that falling apart
of your body and mind in this life
is different from the falling apart
of your body and mind in your past life?
- Is it different things?
- Yeah, they're different things.
GAL TE DE LAS 'DI GZHAN NA
If they were really different things,
,SDUG BSNGAL GZHAN GYIS BYAS 'GYUR ZHING,
,GZHAN DE DAG GIS DE BYAS 'GYUR,
then you could say...
If they were different,
maybe you could say
that the falling apart
of your body and mind
in your last life has
caused the falling apart
of your body and mind in this life.
That's okay.
If you had a body and mind
falling apart in your last life
so you did mean things to other people
to try to fix your falling
apart body and mind,
then you get a new falling
apart body and mind.
Are those the same body and mind,
or are they different body and mind?
- So they're different, right?
- They have to be.
- Then they never touch.
They never make contact.
So how can two things
that never make contact
affect each other?
If you play or shoot a billiard ball
and it hits another billiard ball,
there has to be a point of contact.
And the motion of the first ball
creates the motion of the second ball.
If your past life's
suffering body and mind
impelled your present life's
suffering body and mind,
then they should've made
contact at some point.
But if things exist the
way you think they do,
outside of your seeds, they
can never make contact.
They cannot make contact.
We already went through that.
It's like your foot on the...
Where's the middle part of your foot?
Where does the past meet the present?
Where does the past meet the future?
There cannot be contact between two things
if they are self-existently separate.
If they exist by themselves
from their own side,
they cannot make contact
because they would have
to overlap and they can't.
If they did overlap, then your past life
would be your present
life for a little time.
They can't touch.
There's nowhere where they can touch.
There's no place where they can touch.
If your past life touches
your present life,
then the place where they touch would be
both your present life and your past life.
And that's not possible.
They have to be separate.
If they're completely separate like that,
then by the time your past
life messed up body and mind...
Sorry, if it's still there
you haven't died yet,
and you can't have a
future body and mind yet.
If you have a future body and mind,
then your past body and mind already died.
A thing which is already gone cannot have
a relationship with something that's here.
Not possible.
Something that came the moment before
can never cause something
which is here now
because there's no time for them to touch.
Either the past thing would have to be,
have its toe in the present,
or the present thing would
have to have the edge
of its bottom in the past.
Somebody would have to cross
the line for them to touch.
Got it?
And it's not possible.
It's not possible.
Don't blame something else
for causing your current suffering.
It can't be.
If it's gone, it can't do anything.
If it's not gone, you're
still in your past life.
Okay.
All right, whew.
All right.
I have a picture here of
a finger and a cactus.
This is different from the
other finger and cactus picture.
- Why, Geshe-la?
- There's a space between
the finger and the cactus.
If things never touch each
other, you can't get hurt.
If your finger never touches
the cactus, you can't get hurt.
And the fact is that you can't,
your finger, your present suffering
cannot touch your past life's
suffering, not possible.
Cannot.
Rebecca, if they never touch,
can one hurt the other?
No, if they never touch, then
one cannot cause the other.
Now, if you like insist, yeah,
my current life suffering happens.
Forget, I don't care about it.
And my past life's suffering caused it.
- Did they touch? - No.
- Can a cactus hurt your
finger without touching
if your present life
can have trouble caused
by your past life without touching?
- Yeah, they can.
- Okay, so you should run around
like this all day, ow, ow, ow.
- Why? - Because there's
cactus near Phoenix.
And it doesn't have to
touch you to hurt you.
- Okay, Geshe-la, it does
have to touch me to hurt you.
- Okay, then your past life
has to touch your present life.
- Yeah, well, what's wrong with that?
- They have to overlap.
Then part of your past life
has to be in the present
to touch your present life,
or part of your present life has
to be in the past to get
touched by your past life.
But that's not possible
because your present life
is different from your past life.
If your present life had
to touch your past life,
then you would be in your past life.
Got it?
It's not possible what
you think is happening.
It's not even possible
what the Buddha kept saying
that what you did your past life
is causing you suffering in this life.
That's not possible.
The Buddha? Something's wrong.
A cactus that you never could touch
is making your finger hurt.
That's the same thing.
I'll say it again. Don't look so confused.
Or look confused, that's okay.
If what you did in your
past life is causing
you suffering in the present life,
then the past life has
to touch the present life
in the same way that your
finger has to touch a cactus.
And if your finger can
hurt without touching
the cactus, and if your
present life can have trouble
without touching your past life,
then because there's cactuses in Arizona,
every time you cross the state line
your finger should start hurting.
- Why?
- Because without touching,
they can hurt you.
- What do you mean? What's
that got to do with it?
Because without your past life touching
your present life, the
events of your past life
can hurt your present life,
according to you, Buddha.
Got it?
But they can't touch.
If they touch, then the very beginning
of your present life would
have to be in your past life,
or the very end of your past life
would have to be in your present life.
And then there wouldn't be a difference
between past life and present life.
It doesn't make sense.
- Geshe-la, why are we talking
about this stuff? Who cares?
Who cares because you can't stop suffering
unless you figure out
where it's coming from.
And it's not coming from your past life
because your past life can't
touch your present life.
- Well, where's it coming from?
- You know, you'll get there. Okay.
All right, next verse.
,GAL TE GANG ZAG BDAG GIS NI,
,SDUG BSNGAL BYAS NA GANG BDAG GIS,
,SDUG BSNGAL BYAS PA'I GANG ZAG NI,
,SDUG BSNGAL MA GTOGS GANG ZHIG YIN,
If some kind of... now it's a person.
All right, let's say
if someone else could hurt me, then
,SDUG BSNGAL BYAS NA GANG BDAG GIS,
,SDUG BSNGAL BYAS PA'I GANG ZAG NI,
then that person who caused me pain
SDUG BSNGAL MA GTOGS GANG ZHIG YIN
must cause me pain all the time.
Or they would be pain itself.
If another person can pain
me, then they are pain.
Got it?
If another person can...
We're always blaming our
problems on other people,
all the time, every moment of the day.
But if a person could make you feel pain,
then they would have to be pain.
Because you're feeling
pain when you touch them.
Got it?
And then you could go a different way.
I think you could take
this a different way.
And Choney Lama, if you read Choney Lama,
you can take it this way.
You can look at the picture here.
I don't know, this is a guy in an office.
I don't know if this ever
happened to you in a job
that your boss is yelling at you.
I don't know.
It's almost the definition of a job.
So the boss is yelling at the guy.
Now, who's hurting whom?
Wait, stay there, yeah good.
- Who's hurting whom?
- The boss is hurting the employee, right?
The employee looks sad.
The boss looks happy
because he gets to be the boss.
And he's hurting the person.
So you can say the boss
hurt the employee, right?
Did the employee hurt themself?
Is the boss himself?
Is the boss the employee?
That's the question here.
I mean, that's one of the big
questions of this chapter.
When someone else causes you suffering...
When your boss is yelling at you,
who's yelling at you?
Who caused it?
Yeah, so you're hurting yourself.
You're hurting yourself.
Which we just said is impossible.
Okay.
Pain cannot hurt pain, right?
Think about it.
By the way, this whole
thing gets into blame.
You know, can you blame other people
for the trouble you have?
Or what caused cancer?
If the mantra's going to
work to stop the cancer,
then it's going to have to stop
whatever caused the cancer.
So then you got to look at
what really caused the cancer.
Because if it's the mantra's
job to stop the cancer,
the mantra's going to have to
stop what caused the cancer.
Because if the mantra can't
stop what caused the cancer,
then the more cancer's going to come.
So does the mantra ever
work to stop cancer?
Then it would have to stop the
cause of the cancer, right?
And you have to think about that.
How can the mantra touch
the cause of the cancer
when the cause of the
cancer is already gone.
How can you ever cure
cancer with a mantra?
You would have to stop
the cause of the cancer
which is already gone, anyway.
You don't need the mantras to stop
the cause of the cancer
because the cause of the cancer
is already gone by the
time the cancer's there.
So how are you going to stop the cancer
if you can't stop the cause of the cancer?
How can you make contact with a thing
which is already in the past?
That's like writing your great grandma
a letter or something.
Okay?
Therefore, the way a mantra works
to stop your cancer is not what you think.
You have to collect other seeds.
And again, saving life is great.
Saving some fish's life is good.
And I think it gets you out of your house
and it gets you actually saving
a living being who's in front of you.
And there's nothing as powerful as that.
But I think there are also
lifestyle choices you can make:
about using your car
or using plastic, or things
like that, cutting down trees.
That would save a lot more lives.
Maybe you could do both.
All right.
All right, next verse.
He puts together five, six, and seven.
Here we go.
,GAL TE GANG ZAG GZHAN LAS NI,
,SDUG BSNGAL 'BYUNG NA GZHAN ZHIG GIS,
,SDUG BSNGAL DE BYAS GANG SBYIN DE,
,SDUG BSNGAL MA GTOGS JI LTAR RUNG,
If the pain I have is caused
GAL TE GANG ZAG GZHAN LAS NI
if another person can cause me pain,
SDUG BSNGAL 'BYUNG NA GZHAN ZHIG GIS
then the suffering they
caused me should never stop.
- Why?
- Because if the pain, if the trouble
in my life is really
caused by another person,
then the word "another" means
a person who is not myself.
- Right, right.
- So a person who is not myself caused me
some trouble in my life.
- Right. - That means they
must have touched you.
- Right.
- If they never make
contact with you in any way,
then they can't cause you trouble, right?
- Right.
- So they must have, their
life must've made contact
with your life in some way, right?
- Right.
- So they must overlap
at some point, right?
- No, they just touched me.
They don't overlap.
- Okay. So how do they touch
you without overlapping?
- Well, just the edge of them
touches the edge of my trouble.
- Come on, then there has to be contact.
There has to be some overlap.
- Okay. So there is overlap, Geshe-la.
- Then the other person and your trouble
are partly the same thing.
And any time the person's
there that give you trouble,
I guess there are people like that.
,GAL TE GANG ZAG GZHAN SDUG BSNGAL,
,'BYUNG NA GANG GIS DE BYAS NAS,
,GZHAN LA STER BA'I GANG ZAG GZHAN,
,SDUG BSNGAL MA GTOGS GANG ZHIG YIN,
- According to you someone
else is causing the trouble,
problems in your life.
- Yes, it's my partner.
I don't have trouble.
They give me trouble.
- Okay, so somebody else
gives you trouble, right?
- Right.
- So they have to make contact
with you on some level, right?
They have to make contact
with you to give you trouble, right?
- Yeah.
- So in some way, at some
point they become you.
The past touches the present.
So the last part of the
past is the first part
of the present because
the last part of the past
has to start your trouble, right?
By the way, if the other person
and your trouble starting
were one millisecond apart,
then they couldn't make contact.
There's no point at
which they make contact.
The cause is gone, the result is starting.
- Well, that doesn't make sense
because if the cause causes the result,
then the cause has to share some
milliseconds with the result.
Or else something which is not there
is causing something which is there.
And that's not possible.
That's like a billiard ball
that already fell in the pocket
is making another ball move.
See what I mean? It has to be there.
They have to both be on the table.
So the person who causes
you trouble in your life
has to be in the same moment
and in the same place as you to do that.
- Yeah. - So that means
they're not a cause, right?
- Why not?
- Because they're past already.
By the time the tree grows from a seed,
the seed is gone.
By the time your partner
gives you trouble,
and you got the trouble,
your partner has to be
invisible, not there.
An invisible, non-existent partner,
like a seed that disappeared
after the tree grew,
is causing you trouble, right?
Okay.
,BDAG GIS BYAS PAR MA GRUB PAS,
,SDUG BSNGAL GZHAN GYIS GA LA BYAS,
,GZHAN GYIS SDUG BSNGAL GANG BYED PA,
,DE NI DE YI BDAG BYAS 'GYUR,
So the other guy is...
This is now Choney Lama goes
off on a bit of a tangent.
And I'll go with him.
He says, "When I say your current pain
"is caused by somebody else,
"I just mean the actions taken by
"a life form in the past, say an animal,
"are causing the pain
of a human in this life.
"So I'm not talking about the same person.
That was an animal, this was a human."
"I'm talking about different
life forms," he says.
That's possible.
They're not me.
The animal is a different life form,
somebody other than me.
When I say somebody other
than me has caused me
the trouble in this life I'm saying
this human life's trouble was caused
by someone who was an
animal, or something.
That's the other guy's trying to say.
Then you should have
suffering all the time.
If someone can cause you suffering,
if someone can give you trouble
without making contact with you,
then you should have trouble all the time.
- Why?
- Because they're always
not making contact with you.
Then your whole life
should be trouble all time.
I'll say it again.
If someone can give you trouble
without making contact with you,
then even when they're not
around, you should have trouble.
- Why?
- Because they don't have to make contact
with you to give you trouble.
Then I chose a picture here.
Do you ever give pain to your future self?
There you go, there's the answer.
Yeah, yeah.
I don't know, yesterday
I made sweet rolls.
Someone was teaching me to make
cinnamon rolls for our cafe.
Then I don't know why we all felt,
there were four of us there,
and we all felt that
because we were making them
for a noble purpose we could
eat them as much as we wanted.
And we all ate like
three or four of those.
And then afterwards I was like,
what the heck did I just do?
Yeah, I am causing pain
for my future self.
But how is that if I never touched them?
If I'm gone, if the person who ate
the three or four cinnamon rolls is gone
by the time the other person gets fat,
then can you really say that someone
who's not there is giving someone trouble
to someone who is there?
It's not possible.
It's actually not possible.
- Well, Geshe-la, what's really going on?
Some kind of karmic seed is creating
the eating the cinnamon roll.
And then another karmic seed
is creating the fat person.
But the cinnamon roll
doesn't cause the fat person.
In theory, you should be
able to eat cinnamon rolls
without getting fat.
We're still looking for the sweet spot.
All right.
Let's go onto the next verse.
And I know it's hard.
It's hard to have so much
Nagarjuna in one day.
Hang in there.
,RE ZHIG SDUG BSNGAL BDAG BYAS MIN,
,DE NYID KYIS NI DE MA BYAS,
,GAL TE GZHAN BDAG MA BYAS NA,
,SDUG BSNGAL GZHAN BYAS GA LA 'GYUR,
RE ZHIG SDUG BSNGAL BDAG
GIS BYAS PA MIN PAR THAL
SDUG BSNGAL DE NYID KYIS
NI DE MA BYAS PA'I PHYIR
You can't say that pain causes pain
because the pain that
causes the present pain
would have to be past pain
and that past pain would have to be gone.
RANG GIS RANG NA BYED PA 'GAL BA'I PHYIR,
GAL TE SDUG BSNGAL GZHAN
BDAG GIS MA BYAS NA
SDUG BSNGAL DE GZHAN
GYIS BYAS PAR SMRA BA'ANG
GA LA 'GYUR TE
If I didn't cause my own pain,
and something else caused my own pain,
but also that thing was gone by
the time I had my own pain,
and something that was
gone was causing something
that's not gone.
Okay.
So the picture I have
here is, I don't know why.
No one can cause me pain.
I cannot.
Michael cannot cause
Michael pain by overeating.
Michael at three o'clock
cannot cause trouble
for Michael at four o'clock by
over eating at three o'clock.
- Why?
Because Michael who
overeats at three o'clock
is gone by the time Michael
at four o'clock is suffering.
They never touched.
They never made contact.
So I cannot cause myself pain.
Obviously, if someone else
cooks me cinnamon rolls
and I eat too many of them,
since they never touched me
they didn't cause me the pain, either.
Therefore, I didn't have the pain?
- No, I had the pain.
It was coming from somewhere else.
All right, here we go.
GAL TE, next verse.
,GAL TE RE RES BYAS GYUR NA,
,SDUG BSNGAL GNYIS KAS BYAS PAR 'GYUR,
,BDAG GIS MA BYAS GZHAN MA BYAS,
,SDUG BSNGAL RGYU MED GA LA 'GYUR,
Then he skips over quickly
the other two possibilities.
- Why?
Say again?
- [Woman] Both and neither.
- Yeah, both and neither.
Both Geshe-la and somebody else
causes Geshe-la to get overweight.
Or nobody causes Geshe-la
to get overweight.
Neither Geshe-la nor
anyone else causes Geshe-la
to get overweight.
And he just dismisses those two.
Okay.
Picture?
It's a picture of two hands
solving a puzzle, I think.
Yeah, anyway, it's not both me
and someone else causing my pain.
And it's not nobody causing my pain.
Nobody causing my pain is easy.
- But Geshe-la, how can
you say that it's not me
and somebody else causing my pain?
Because they are gone by
the time you have the pain.
And something that's not
there cannot cause pain.
All right, here we keep going, next verse.
,SDUG BSNGAL 'BA' ZHIG RNAM PA BZHI,
,YOD MA YIN PAR MA ZAD KYI,
,PHYI ROL DNGOS PO DAG LA YANG,
,RNAM PA BZHI PO YOD MA YIN,
He says, "Look, we just
finished a discussion
of suffering from four points of view."
Does suffering cause suffering?
Does something else cause suffering?
Does both itself and something
else cause suffering?
Or does suffering happen "ahetuka",
"without any cause at all".
And he said no.
He said no to all four.
Then he said, "Take that principle
and apply it to everything
else in your life."
PHYI ROL DNGOS PO RNAMS LA YANG
Apply it to all the things
around you in your world.
All the things around you in your world
are also not caused by themselves,
are not caused by something else,
are not caused by both, and
are not caused by nothing.
But they are caused, so
how does that happen?
From seeds in your mind.
You create, your mind creates the cause.
Your mind creates the result.
Your mind creates the connection
between the cause and the result,
but the cause doesn't cause the result.
That's a fallacy. That's wrong.
That means that everything everyone
has ever done on this planet
who didn't understand
emptiness was mistaken.
Every action taken in the
last few million years
by any person in the world was mistaken
and didn't do what it was supposed to do.
It had no relationship
to what they wanted.
Every single action in human history
was worthless and useless.
All right.
And that is the joyful
end of this first class.
Every action taken by any living being,
animal or human, in the
history of this world
if they didn't understand these things,
was useless and wrong.
Okay, see you guys in the next class.